<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An epistle of the p[ro]phete Hieremie</title>
            <title>Bible. O.T. Baruch. English. Selections.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1539</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 14 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 10 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A16003</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 2792</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S113316</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99848552</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99848552</idno>
            <idno type="VID">13653</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A16003)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 13653)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 642:03)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An epistle of the p[ro]phete Hieremie</title>
                  <title>Bible. O.T. Baruch. English. Selections.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[20] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Iohn Redman for Roberte Redman],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Imprinted in Southwarke :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1539?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Taken out of the sixth chapter of Baruch.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication and printer from colophon; suggested publication date from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴ B²  C⁴.</note>
                  <note>Formerly also STC 14499.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:13653:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13653:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>An epiſtle of the ꝓphete Hiere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie.<g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="translator_to_friend">
            <pb facs="tcp:13653:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13653:2"/>
            <head>¶The tranſlatour of this worke vnto a certayne frende of his, ſendeth gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynge.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SYr</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>after moſt hartie recommen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, it may lyke you to vnder<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtande that I write vnto you at this tyme for the accomplyſſhement of my promyſe, for you remembre (I am ſure) that in our laſte co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication had together, you deſyred effectually to knowe myne opinion concernynge Ymagery, wherin at that tyme, thoughe ꝑaduenture for defaute of lerning, I was not able to ſatisfie your mynde, yet for as moche as at this day, the ſame mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is put in queſtion, and dyuers great lerned me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> do vary in opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s vpon the ſame, I thought it not vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uenie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to take ſome further payne for to enſerche the treuthe therof. And ſo peruſynge dyuers great au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors,
<pb facs="tcp:13653:3"/> I fortuned in the redyng of the olde teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, otherwyſe called the Byble, to fynde out y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſixte chap. of Baruch the prophete, whiche by cauſe it entreateth principally and all together of Ymagerye, for the ſatisfieng of your deſyre, I tranſla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted &amp; drewe in to englyſſhe as nere as I myght, accordyng to the pure truthe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> texte: wherby, I doubt nothyng, but you ſhalbe clerely put out of all doubte and errour / if ye can fynde in your harte to beſtowe a lytle of your leaſure in the reding of hit. For I do aduertiſe you not onely rede it / but alſo exactely and throughly to ponder &amp; marke euery poynt therof. And for the declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of my mynde herin / I haue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways thought that for bicauſe theſe Ymages lacke y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vſe of the .v. ſenſis, and beſydes that in proceſſe of tyme do both corrupte and conſume lyke
<pb facs="tcp:13653:3"/> as dothe golde / ſyluer / ſtone / and wodde / and the ſtuffe and mattiere wherof they be made, I ſuppoſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to haue none other ſupernaturall vertue / than they had before they were made into Ymages. And not withſtandyng that there hap ſome true and vnfayned myracles to be done at the places wher ſuche yma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges be worſhypped / yet I thynke that they be not done by the vertue of thoſe ymages / nor of god for the ymages ſake / but to thentent that the people ſhuld know y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ſayntꝭ, whom thymages do repreſent and bringe vnto our reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brance, were y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> true &amp; faythfull ſeruantes of god in prechyng &amp; teachyng his worde. But I wyll deteyne you no longer from the redynge of Baruch his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle, wherin (bicauſe it is the very ſcripture &amp; worde of god) you ſhall perceyue the effecte of this matter
<pb facs="tcp:13653:4"/> moche better than I or any other can open or declare vnto you. And thus fare ye well.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <head>The copye of an Epiſtle, the whiche Hieremie the prophete ſent vnto the chyldren of Iſrahel, beinge in captiuite vnder Nabu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chodonozor the kyng of Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon, for to inſtruct them as he was co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded by god, taken out of the .vi. chap. of Baruch.</head>
            <pb facs="tcp:13653:4"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Ycauſe of the ſynnes that ye haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mytted before God, ye ſhalbe ledde priſoners in to Babylon by Nabu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chodonozor kyng of the Babylo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, whan ye therfore ſhall come vnto Babylon, ye ſhalbe there many ye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res and longe tyme vnto .vii. gene<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rations, but after that, I ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer you from the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s in peas, Than ſhall ye ſe gods of golde, of ſyluer, of ſtone, and of tree, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhalbe borne vpon mens ſhulders, puttynge the people in feare. Beware therfore that ye do not lyke vnto the ſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, and that ye drede them not, nor be moued w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> any feare. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore whan ye ſhal ſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhyppyng before and behynde, ſay in your hartes, Lorde god, it is y<hi rend="sup">u</hi>, whiche muſte be worſhypped, And myne angell is with you, &amp; I my
<pb facs="tcp:13653:5"/> ſelfe ſhall require your ſoules. For the wod of them is framed &amp; faſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by the carpentours, and thoſe that be of golde &amp; ſyluer, are falſe, and can not ſpeake. And lyke as apparell is made for a virgin that loueth, ſo are they made of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> golde y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they haue receyued. Theyr gods haue golden crownes on theyr hed<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whiche the preſtes do take the golde and ſyluer, and deuide it amonge them ſelues. They gyue alſo therof vnto harlottes, &amp; gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſſhe hores therwith. And whan they haue receiued it agayne of the harlots, they garnyſſhe theyr gods therwith, yet can they not be kepte from ruſtyng and vermyne. For whan they be couered w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> garme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes of purple, the preſtes muſt be fayne to make clene the faces of them, by cauſe of the duſt of the houſe, wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>of there is moche plentie in thoſe
<pb facs="tcp:13653:5"/> parties. Some alſo haue ſeptres in theyr handes lyke vnto men, &amp; lyke vnto iudges of a realme, the which putteth not hym to dethe that tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpaſeth agaynſt them. Some alſo haue ſwordes in theyr handes and axes, yet can not they delyuer them ſelues from batayle, nor fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theues. wherfore be it knowen vnto you, that they be no gods, therfore do ye no worſhyp vnto them. And lyke as a mans veſſell whan it is broke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſeruethe to no purpoſe, euen ſo be theyr goddes, whan they are ſet vp in a houſe, their eies are full of duſt by reaſon of their fete that come in. And lyke as dores are made faſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout hym y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hath offended a kynge, or as a corps that is brought vnto his graue, is kept in, Euen ſo do the preeſtis make ſure the doores with barres and lockes, to thentent that they ſhall not be robbed of theues.
<pb facs="tcp:13653:6"/> The people do lyght candels befor<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> them, and that in great nombre, of the whiche they ſe not one, for they are as it were blockes in an houſe. And they ſay that the ſerpentes of the erthe do lycke theyr hartes, wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they do eate them &amp; their garme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, and yet they feele them not. Theyr facis are made blacke with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſmoke that is in the houſe. The howlets and ſwalowes, and the byrdes do flee vpon theyr heddes, ye and alſo the wawlynge cattes, wherby ye may knowe that they are no gods<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> therfore do ye not feare them. The golde alſo which they haue to make them glorious, wyll not glyſter, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepte y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ruſt be ſkoured of. For wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they were fyrſt caſte, they felte no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thyng. They were bought with all maner of prices, yet is there no ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite in them. For lacke of fete, they are caryed on folkꝭ ſhoulders, wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>by
<pb facs="tcp:13653:6"/> the people may perceyue their im<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>potencie. Confounded be they ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore that worſhyppe them. And for that cauſe, if they hap to fal downe on the erth, they are not able to riſe by them ſelues. And agayn, if one do ſet them vpryghte, they can not ſtande by them ſelues, but men be fayne for to ſtay them vp with their ſhoulders, lyke as they do corpſys. Theyr preeſtis do ſelle that that is offered vnto them, and abuſe it, ye and theyr women do take therof, and gyue neuer a whyt vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſyck nor vnto the poore women vnpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryfyed and hauynge theyr flowres do handell of theyr ſacrifices. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge therfore that ye do knowe by theſe thinges, that they be no gods, do not feare them. For what cauſe are they called gods? bycauſe wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men do offer all maner of thynges vnto thoſe gods of golde, of ſiluer,
<pb facs="tcp:13653:7"/> and of tree, and preſtes do ſyt in the houſes of them, with iagged veſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, hauynge theyr heddes and berdes ſhauen, whoſe heddes are bare. And they rore cryeng out vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theyr gods, lyke as they do at the ſupper of one y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is deed. The preſtes take away theyr garme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with do clothe theyr wyues &amp; theyr chyldren. And if any do them di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpleaſure, or do them pleaſure, they are not able to requite it, no more are they able to make a kynge, nor to depoſe. Se<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>blably they can gyue no ryches, nor can reuenge theyr harme. If any haue made a vowe vnto them, and hath not ꝑfourmed it, they do not require it. They ſaue no man from dethe, neither do they defende the weake from the mygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye, They reſtore not the blynde vnto ſyght, neyther do they delyuer any man from neceſſite. They take
<pb facs="tcp:13653:7"/> no pytie of the wydowe, neither do they any good vnto orphelyns.</p>
            <p>Theyr goddes of tree, ſtone, golde, and ſyluer, be lyke vnto ſtoones of the mou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tayne. And they that wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhyppe them ſhall be confounded. Howe than may it be ſuppoſed or ſayd that they be gods? Moreouer the Caldees do no honour vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whiche whan they perceyued that the dombe coude not ſpeke, they pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſented it vnto Bel, prayinge hym y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he wold make it to ſpeke, as though the thynges that moue not, myght haue any ſenſe or felyng. And they them ſelfes whan they ꝑceyue this, wyll forſake them. For theyr gods them ſelues lacke theyr ſenſes. women alſo beinge gyrded w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des do ſyt in the hyghe wayes, bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge the leues of the Olyue trees, And whan it fortuneth that one of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is taken vp by any man paſſing
<pb facs="tcp:13653:8"/> by the hyghe way, and ſlepeth with hym, ſhe vpbraydeth her neyghbour therwith, that ſhe is not eſtemed ſo worthye as her ſelfe, and that her corde is not broken, but all thinges that be done vnto them are falſe. Howe than may hit be ſuppoſed or ſayd, that they be goddes? For they are made by workemen and golde ſmythes, They ſhalbe none other thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges, but euen as it pleaſeth pree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes to haue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. The goldſmythes alſo that make them, lyue not euer. Howe is it poſſyble than y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thinges of theyr makyng ſhulde be goddis? But they haue lefte fayned thinges and opprobred to them y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhal come after them. For whan warre ſhall chaunce vnto them and aduerſyte, the preſtes do immagyne wher they may hyde them ſelues with them. Howe than may it be beleued, that theſe are goddes? The whiche can
<pb facs="tcp:13653:8"/> neither ſaue them ſelues from ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayle, nor delyuer them ſelues from aduerſities. for al be it they be made of woode, of ſtone, of golde, and of ſyluer, it ſhall be knowen after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde, through out all nations, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they are counterfet thinges, And it ſhalbe manyfeſt vnto kynges, that they are no goddes, but the workes of mans handes, and y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> no worke of God is in them, wherby than it is euident that they be no goddes, but the workes of mannes handes, &amp; that no worke of God is in them. They conſtitute no kynge in any realme, nor wyll ſende rayne vnto men. They wyll diſcerne no iuge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, neither wyll they defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treys from iniuryes. For they can do nothyng no more than y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> crowes that are betwyxte the ſkye and the erthe. For if there chaunce any fyre vpon the houſe of thoſe goddes of
<pb facs="tcp:13653:9"/> tree, of golde, and of ſyluer, theyr preſtes forthwith wyll flee, &amp; ſaue them ſelues, but theyr goddes ſhall be burned in the myddes lyke as blockes, and wyll not withſtande any kyng nor batayle. Howe than may it be eſtemed or ſuffered, that they ſhuld be goddes? Theſe gods of tree, of ſtone, of golde, and of ſyluer, the which are of les ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth than are the wycked, can not ſaue them ſelfes from theues. They ſhal robbe them of theyr golde &amp; ſyluer, and theyr garmentes, wher w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they be clothed, &amp; yet can not helpe them ſelues. Better it is therfore to be a kynge that ſheweth his puiſſaunce, or to be a profytayle veſſell in an houſe, wherin the owner may take pleſure, or to be a dore in an houſe, that kepeth the ſtuffe in ſaufegarde than to be falſe goddes. The ſonne and the mone, and the ſterres that
<pb facs="tcp:13653:9"/> do ſhyne, whan they are ſent forth for neceſſary thynges, do obey.</p>
            <p>Semblably the lyghtnynge whan it apperethe, it is viſible, And lyke wyſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wynde doth blowe in euery contreye. And the cloudes (whan they are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded by god to paſſe through the worlde) they do accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge as they be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded. The fyre alſo that is ſent from aboue for to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſume hylles and woddes, doth as it is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded. But theſe are not lyke neyther in beautie nor in vertue, vnto any of theſe thynges. wherfore it is neither to be eſtemed nor ſayde, that they be goddes, for aſmoche as they can not gyue iuge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, nor profyte any thynge vnto men. Ye therfore knowynge y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they be no goddes, do not feare them, for they wyl neyther curſe kynges, nor bleſſe them. Alſo they do not ſhewe vnto the people ſignes from heuen,
<pb facs="tcp:13653:10"/> neyther ſhall they ſhyne as the ſon, ne gyue lyghte as the mone. The beaſtis are better than they, which can flee vnder houſes, &amp; helpe them ſelues. And ſo hit can appere vnto you by no meanes, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they are gods, for whiche cauſe do not feare them. For lyke as in a place where gour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des do growe, feare kepeth nothi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g, euen ſo be theyr goddes of wodde, ſyluer, and golde. They be in lyke caſe as is a whyte thorne in a gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deyn, wherupo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> euery byrde ſitteth. Semblably theyr goddes of wood, golde, and ſyluer, are lyke vnto a corps that is caſt into the darke. Ye may knowe alſo by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> purple &amp; the other paynted colours, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they haue vpon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they be no gods. And in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cluſion they ſhalbe eaten vp, &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buke ſhal come in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> contree, Better is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> iuſt ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which hath no ymages for he ſhalbe fartheſt from rebukes.</p>
            <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
            <trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:13653:10"/>Thus endeth the diuine epiſtle of the prophet Hieremie, diſſwa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dyng the people from Ydolatry, that is to ſay, worſhyppyng of Ymages.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>Imprinted in Southwarke by Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Redman for Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berte Red<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="license">
            <p>¶CVM PRIVILEGIO</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
